<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Differences in matters of religion, betweene the easterne and westerne churches VVherein the Romane Church may see her selfe charged with as many errours, as shee falsly layeth to the charge of other churches in Europe. Gathered by Irenæus Rodoginus.</title>
            <author>Rodoginus, Irenaeus.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1625</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 96 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10875</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21141</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116064</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851281</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851281</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16551</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10875)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16551)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1254:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Differences in matters of religion, betweene the easterne and westerne churches VVherein the Romane Church may see her selfe charged with as many errours, as shee falsly layeth to the charge of other churches in Europe. Gathered by Irenæus Rodoginus.</title>
                  <author>Rodoginus, Irenaeus.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[40], 45, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Augustine Mathevves for Iohn Budge, and are to be sold at the signe of the Windmill in Britaines-Burse,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1625.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Irenæus Rodoginus" is probably a pseudonym.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Differences betweene the easterne and westerne churches.</note>
                  <note>Variant: imprint has ".. signe of the Harrow in Britaines Burse. ..".</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Schism --  Eastern and Western Church --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16551:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>DIFFERENCES IN MATTERS OF RELIGION, BE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Eaſterne and Weſterne Churches.</p>
            <p>Wherein the Romane Church <hi>may ſee her ſelfe charged with</hi> as many Errours, as ſhee falſly layeth to the charge of other Churches in <hi>Europe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Gathered by <hi>Irenaeus Rodoginus.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Ioan. 15.17.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by AVGVSTINE MATHEVVES for <hi>Iohn Budge,</hi> and are to be ſold at the ſigne of the Windmill in <hi>Britaines</hi> Burſe. 1625.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:16551:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16551:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, and moſt magnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Patterne of inuincible courage, my ſingular good Lord and Patron, <hi>George,</hi> Earle of <hi>Engie,</hi> Lord <hi>Gordon</hi> and <hi>Badenocht,</hi> Sonne to the thriſe-Noble and Puiſſant, L. <hi>George,</hi> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe of <hi>Huntley,</hi> Earle of <hi>Engie,</hi> L. <hi>Gordon</hi> and <hi>Badenocht,</hi> Sheriffe principall of <hi>Aberden</hi> and <hi>Invirneſſe,</hi> L. of <hi>Oboyne</hi> and <hi>Strathaune,</hi> Baron of <hi>Achindowne, Melgon</hi> and <hi>Gartly, &amp;c.</hi> all increaſe of honour in this life, and eternall happineſſe in the life to come.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O lay aſide (right Honourable) all the officious com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plements, vſed by most men now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daies to make way for the purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the fauour of high and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent
<pb facs="tcp:16551:3"/>
Perſonages; What your Lordſhip is to me, J my ſelfe know beſt: neither will J expoſe it to the view of Buyers, it being vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vendible, yea, vnestimable. J offer to your Lordſhips favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Patronage this little Treatiſe of lamentable Diſſentions, neuer (for ought I know) heeretofore collected into one Packet: and as yet rather a Rapſodie, then a Methodicall Relation of Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences. Your Lordſhip loueth V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; This emboldeneth me. Your Lordſh. hateth Schiſme, for which I heartily thanke God, beſeeching him vpon the very bended knees of my ſoule, that you and all ſuch, eminent in Learning, Wiſedome, and Pietie, may by all meanes
<pb facs="tcp:16551:3"/>
poſsible endeauour to helpe to pull downe theſe ill-compoſed walls of Schiſme, and to reare vp the beautifull and long-deſired wall of Peace. God preſerue your Honour, increaſe your Wealth, and reſtore you fully to your for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Health.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Lordſhips daily Orator, in all duetie and good affection moſt humble,</hi> Irenaeus Rodoginus.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:16551:4"/>
            <head>To his moſt louing Maſter, <hi>I. R.</hi> the Contriuer of this Worke.</head>
            <l>HEre Schiſmes, and rents, and breaches manifold,</l>
            <l>(With weeping eyes, which now I doe behold)</l>
            <l>Thou haſt layd out before the view of men,</l>
            <l>With thine exact, and Peace-deſiring Pen.</l>
            <l>Well doſt thou wiſh, for which I wiſh thee well:</l>
            <l>Yet wiſhing doth not fiery darts repell.</l>
            <l>But, Oh that Kings and Potentates their beſt</l>
            <l>Would doe, and ſo yeeld to thy ſweet requeſt:</l>
            <l>Then ſhould Peace ſhine, and Gordian knots now faſt</l>
            <l>Diſſolued bee, and into <hi>Lethe</hi> caſt.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>Miſonices Renatus.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:16551:4"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hriſtian Catholicke Reader, (whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer thou art) hauing taken ſome paines in collecting theſe differences, I recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend vnto thee, the vſing &amp; peruſing of them. Come with a minde voide of preiudice, and behold the ſchiſms of the Church, the lamentable and pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull ruine of Chriſtian people; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe men by ſpeedy repentance and earneſt deuotion to God, the Authour of peace and concord, preuent theſe ſure imminent perils and dangers. The coate of Chriſt is rent, his garment
<pb facs="tcp:16551:5"/>
is torne in peeces, the world is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted and diſtempered with the rag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing waues of opinion. Some Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, either in ambitious and extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uagant thoughts are become furious, giuing out idle fancies for ſound and ſolid nouriſhment;<note place="margin">Iere. 14.14.</note> (the Prophet cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth them falſe viſions and the deceite of their owne heart,) or elſe (as it is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer in ſchiſme) are miſled, yea rather muzled by preiudice: ſo that there is no ſauce, (be it neuer ſo ſweete) which can taſte well to their pre-ocupied pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats, but only that, which reliſheth the venemous gall of bitternes, whereby they may worke the bane and vtter ouerthrow of them which are of a contrary mind<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the firſt ſort of theſe men are led to foſter Schiſme againſt conſcience; to maintaine themſelues in Dignities, Wealth, Peace and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion. Of which is a number of the learned'ſt, and moſt polliticke Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Prelates, Cardinalls, Doctors,
<pb facs="tcp:16551:5"/>
and Preachers in the Romiſh Church. The ſecond is hurled forward, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any reſpect, only blowne vp with fooliſh zeale lacking knowledge; ſo that there is not a moule-hill this day in Religion betweene the one ſide and the other, which to them ſeemeth not to bee an high mountaine. They can ſee nothing but through perſpectiues, making things a far diſtant ſeem to be very neere. Or rather they behold the controuerſies of Religion, as they doe the Moone in the Horizon, which ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to bee a great deale bigger, (though more diſtant the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Zenith) then when ſhee hath iournied a good way in her courſe. And that, becauſe of the tranſparant and watriſh bodies of the Clowdes interiacent, which di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide the rayes of their ſight, and let them not behold that luminous body <hi>in rei veritate,</hi> as it is, but ſo farre as they can: till the impediments be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued. The firſt ſort, though their
<pb facs="tcp:16551:6"/>
power and meanes be greater, yet their action is leſſe; nor yet is it ſo rigorous in playing a part in this dolefull Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedie of Church and State deuiſion: ſeeing preferment breedeth emulation from without, and arrogancie as a do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſticke and indiuiduall <hi>Achates,</hi> which let neuer the giddy multitude ſo doat and admire their actions, as that they can lead by their carriage this wild and vntam'd Colt, to be the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan of vpholding Schiſme and idle o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions. The other ſort deſpiſing (as it were) dignities, miſregarding mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, leauing Father and Mother, Wife and Children, yea all things (ſo they ſay) for Chriſt and his Goſpell, (well) take themſelues either to a ſpeculatiue and retyred life; and ſo they ſhunne the thunderbolts of enuie and hatred; or elſe they chooſe an actiue kind of life, to preach the Word in pulpits, to teach it in Schooles, or to giue priuate informations in doctrine and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,
<pb facs="tcp:16551:6"/>
by conference, diſputations, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonings, by writing to thoſe, who are farre diſtant from them, and by lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing monuments of their diligence and induſtry to future ages, for eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizing their name and pofeſsion. Both theſe ſorts bring admiration, admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion enquirie, enquirie notice of the reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of their doings, notice breedeth liking of their perſons and profesſion, (eſpecially whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the dunghill of fooliſh and idolatrous opinions is luſtred &amp; guilded with the gliſtring colours of Rhetoricke, which in the eares of Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance ſoundeth as ſweete, as the harmonicall concords of the ſweeteſt-breaſted Quiriſters.) Liking of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion is that, which maketh men now a daies runne to all theſe heady courſes, to murder &amp; maſſacre poore Chriſtians, to ruinate Cities, diſpeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Kingdomes, kill Princes, inuent Gunpowder Treaſons; yea what not? And doe the inuentors of theſe miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes,
<pb facs="tcp:16551:7"/>
&amp; deuiſers of diuerſitie, with the vpholders thereof, come firſt vpon the Stage to act the Prologue of theſe turbulent Tragedies? No ſurely. They lie ſecurely all the night long in their beds, in the day time they meditate quietly in their cloſets how to vphold theſe pretty tricks, when as the poore Chriſtian world is trauelling thorow moore and marriſh, caſting ditches and Trenches to defend or offend. And finally the common-wealth is the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tall cauſe led by the circlings of theſe vpper powers, in zeale and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to rippe out her bowels from her belly. Good Lord Ieſu! when ſhal theſe endleſſe &amp; needleſſe iarring haue an end? when ſhall the Church Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke liue in vnion of Faith, and communion of Charity? When will the Romiſh Cleargie lay aſide (yea rather baniſh to Hell) prepoſterous (yea rather helliſh) meanes, vſed for the obtaining of ſecondarie ends, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
<pb facs="tcp:16551:7"/>
and Lucre: for which they ſo maintaine the lamentable rent of the Chriſtian world? Good Ieſu! when will the Laytie (the wiſer and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neder ſort I meane) ſee with cleere-ſighted eyes, and vnderſtand with minds free of preiudice; how they are hood-wincked in an implicit and heart-tongue-tyed faith, beleeuing all things, yet beleeuing nothing; ſeeing they know not what they beleeue; being like that mad franticke fellow in the Poet, who thought hee was ſound in health, though poſſeſſed with a deadly ague? Poore people the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie muſt inſtruct you; but you ſhould be <hi>Berians;</hi> the Clergie muſt direct you in <hi>materia fidei:</hi> yet, you ought to enquire for <hi>via trita &amp; regia,</hi> the common path, the by-wayes of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of <hi>Schoole quiddities,</hi> and imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginary ſcar-Crowes, (hereſie, to their conceite) and (as they informe you) the contrarieties in matters indefini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,
<pb facs="tcp:16551:8"/>
the poſitiue reſolutions of matters coniecturall; yea of ſome things that are not, haue not beene, nor euer ſhall be, haue ſo marred the Chriſtian peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: that now adayes moſt men are become <hi>Laodiceans,</hi> (not in matters of opinion, which would to God all men were, but in things moſt neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to bee done and beleeued) neither hot nor cold. The reſt in the fierie hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of contention, thinke verily that it is impoſsible that their brethren ſhould be ſaued, if they keepe their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, whereas their brethren are more aſſured of their owne ſaluation then they of theirs, though they thinke that they haue their ſaluation ſealed by a moſt euident and manifeſt demonſtration.<note place="margin">Heb. 10.30.</note> O cruell madneſſe ſo to incroach vpon Gods propertie, who ſaith, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>engeance is mine, and I will repay.</hi> In whoſe hands is life and death, who only in his ſecret Cabinet hath ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruled Fate, fortune, and all the vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable
<pb facs="tcp:16551:8"/>
diuination of theſe perempto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie diuinators, who likewiſe keepeth curſing and bleſsing to himſelfe. Where is that wonted charity, when it was ſaid, if any man thinketh other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, God ſhall reueale it. <hi>Origen Hom.</hi> 5. <hi>in Leuit.</hi> ſaith that there bee ſome doctrines in Scripture ſo ſecret, that euen Prieſts ſhall not find them out. But that golden ſentence of Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt. in Geneſ. ad. lit. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>Cap.</hi> 9. muſt be euer in my mouth and in my heart, <hi>Ea moderatio eſt ſeruanda, vt in profundo ſcripturae ſenſu, praeſtemus diligentiam re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirendi, quam affirmandi temeritatem,</hi> as for the deepe meaning of Scripture, we muſt be of ſuch a moderation, that wee may rather ſeeme to be diligent ſearchers then bold and raſh in affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming. <hi>Cyr. Alex. contra Anthrop. C.</hi> 2. <hi>Subtiles eiuſmodi at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> admodum tritae quaeſtiones non tam demonſtratione dogma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tica, quam dubitatione &amp; diſcuſsione con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecturali indigent,</hi> ſuch ſubtil queſtions
<pb facs="tcp:16551:9"/>
ſtand more in need of doubting the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of demonſtration. And ſo he endeth <hi>Quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque ergo ſacra ſcriptura non dicit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertè, latere oportet &amp; ſilentio praeterire,</hi> whatſoeuer things the Scripture ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth not plainely, they muſt not bee expreſſed, but rather paſt ouer with ſilence. If this moderation of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment this day were in the Chriſtian Churches; Greeke or Romiſh, ſhould the Turkiſh tyrannie of the faithleſſe <hi>Ottoman,</hi> ſo ouer-rule the flouriſhing and moſt famous part of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome? Could the ſworne enemies of Chriſt erect their blaſphemous Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues and Mahumetan worſhip, euen in the gorgious and ſtately Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entall Baſilicks? Should <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> that Queene of beauty and once Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of <hi>Europe,</hi> now bee a denne of Dragons and a manſion of Infidels? Should the inuincible Iſlands of <hi>Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſpont, Aegaeum,</hi> &amp; <hi>Mediterranian</hi> Seas guarded by Nature wonderfully, with
<pb facs="tcp:16551:9"/>
Rocks and ſteepe Mountaines for walls, with the waues of the Ocean beating their ſides vnceſſantly for ditches: Should they (I ſay) now bee ſubiect to that monſter of Man-kinde, terrour of the Earth and waſter of Chriſtendome? <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Philippi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> ſheweth the reaſon, <hi>Euery man ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth his owne things; and not the things of Chriſt.</hi> This is that, which bringeth this depopulation and ſeruitude, this hard and cruell yoake both vpon ſoule and body. Diſcord and diſſention is is the <hi>puppis &amp; prora.</hi> Men ſhould la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to pluck out thoſe things which either hinder the growth of the good ſeede of the Word, or which let the Word from being receiued; and ſo all men ſhould liue in charity, for as <hi>Greg. in poſt.</hi> ſaith, <hi>diſcordes tamdiu nullum bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni operis ſacrificium deo immolant, quamdiu a proximorum charitate diſcordant,</hi> Men can offer no acceptable ſacrifice to God, ſo long as they are at variance
<pb facs="tcp:16551:10"/>
with their brethren. S. <hi>Hieron. ad Rom. Vbi diſſentio &amp; invidia, ibi chorus non eſt:</hi> Where there is diſcord and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy, there is no friendly fellowſhip; and where there is no fellowſhip, there is no ſtrength, but all are weake: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as if they would ioyne hands toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, they would be ſtrong enough for all their aduerſaries.</p>
            <p>O poore Chriſtians, running to your owne murder, and which is worſt, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighting in ſelfe-killing, thinking all is well, if you die in your own conceited cauſe, with the approbation of your hooded Conſcience. I aske you, what thinke you ſhall be your reward from God for dying in ſuch quarrells, as the moſt part of you doe? The Romiſh Church will condemne the Greekiſh, as Schiſmatike, for her <hi>Fermamentum;</hi> The Greekiſh will excommunicate and abiure the Romiſh Church for her <hi>Azyma.</hi> And ſo the wiſer ſort can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but either laugh with <hi>Democritus,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:16551:10"/>
or lament with <hi>Heraclitus,</hi> beholding this mad folly. Greece will not faſt vpon Saterdayes, yet Rome will: and herein lieth the plea and action. Good Lord! what ſhall wee ſay? I muſt heere inſert the ſpeeches of <hi>Manuel Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leca,</hi> a Greeke, from whom I haue lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned all theſe fooliſh and futile diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences for the moſt part, <hi>Lib.</hi> 4. <hi>contra Graecos, cap. de Ieiunio. Omnino autem de cibis &amp; potibus, &amp; indumentis quae<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ipſe &amp;c.</hi> The Grecians (ſaith he) make the Latines Heretikes, becauſe they vſe not the cuſtomes in meat, drinke, and clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, which they vſed in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: for they would haue all the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the earth (if it were poſsible) to obſerue the ſame Ceremonies, which they doe; not knowing that they themſelues may bee alſo rebuked in the ſame, and ſuch like. And yet it is not impoſsible, that all the world ſhould be brought vnder one and the ſame rule, the differences of tongues,
<pb facs="tcp:16551:11"/>
of manners, and ſuch like things being no hinderance for the effecting of this; for when the Apoſtles had viſited the whole world, they inforced none to change their ceremonious Cuſtomes in common things; but exhorting them to hold faſt 10. or 12. princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall Articles of Religion, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe them; they made no mention of any thing elſe, vnleſſe it did openly gain-ſtand the former articles. <hi>O aureum dictum!</hi> a ſaying to be regiſtred in the hearts, &amp; printed vpon the fore-heads of turbulent and furious ſpirits now adayes, who cannot indure, but with gnaſhing of teeth, that any Church or Countrey baptize with croſsing after, haue Organs or Altars, Curats, or Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>benders, vſe Cap or Surpliſe, becauſe they haue them not, or rather will not haue them at all; or elſe becauſe they are in vſe in the Popiſh Church, (a fine reaſon indeed.) I wonder that theſe men can indure preaching in a Church
<pb facs="tcp:16551:11"/>
built by a Papiſt, or ringing of Bells, this being a cuſtome vſed by the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, or giuing of thankes after meat, ſeeing the Papiſt doth the like. And as thoſe men loathe euery Ceremonie which the Romane Church hath: ſo doth the Romiſh Church deteſt the Greeke Church, and ſhee no leſſe the Romiſh: ſo that this queſtion being propounded to <hi>Chomatianus,</hi> by a Greeke, Whether it was lawfull for a Greeke to enter into a Latin Church, and worſhip there being deſired; he anſwered negatiuely, <hi>Tom.</hi> 1. <hi>Iuris Grae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corum. Balſamon</hi> ſaith, That all the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies of the Latin church diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring from the ceremonies of the holy Catholike Church, (he meaneth the Greeke Church) are to be reiected, and no ſocietie to be kept with the Latines, <hi>Ibidem. Cabaſila</hi> propounded a queſtion to <hi>Iohn Biſhop Citrius,</hi> if the Greeks which were buried in the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine Churches, and had Hymnes ſung
<pb facs="tcp:16551:12"/>
at their Funeralls, could be ſubiect to cenſure. Yea, after the Councell of <hi>Florence,</hi> the rage of the Grecians was ſo great againſt thoſe that were at the Councell, and accorded to ſome Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles for the purchaſing of ayd againſt the <hi>Turke,</hi> who at that time tooke the neuer enough lamented citie of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople,</hi> that when they came home, though ſubiect to the vncertaine and faithleſſe mercy of the barbarous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querour, they excommunicated all thoſe who accorded to the Articles: and when their ſoules had taken their good night in parting from the body, they caſt them like dogs into ditches, and denied them moſt barbarouſly the benefit of Chriſtian buriall.</p>
            <p>The Latine Church not being wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to be inferiour to her ſiſter in theſe prankes, doth ſerue the Proteſtants af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the like manner: for if any of the reformed Church die amongſt them, his ſoule is determinately ſent packing
<pb facs="tcp:16551:12"/>
to Hell by the Popes<note n="*" place="margin">For euery Holy Thurſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day he curſeth all Proteſtants.</note> curſing; his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy it muſt either lie vnburied at all, or elſe it muſt be carried to ſome place where Proteſtants vſe to interre their dead. O my ſoule! what ſhalt thou think? How muſt thou meditate vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the barbarous and beaſtly crueltie againſt the dead bodies of them, who liued to the eyes of all, vnblameable, (perchance) and died in the faith of the Lord <hi>Ieſus,</hi> holding him onely their Redeemer, Sauiour, and Mediatour, baptized in the Name of the Father, Sonne, and Holy Ghoſt, giuing teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of their comfort and gladneſſe in the houre of their death, ſhewing by their cheerfulneſſe the Prognoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations and infallible tokens of their entrance and fore-ſmelling of endleſſe glory. Such mens bones doe the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts debarre from reſting in that Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Grand-mother <hi>Tellus,</hi> where the former Saints bodies, which now in part triumph in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light,
<pb facs="tcp:16551:13"/>
reſt, waiting for a glorious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, a perfect beatitude, with a full and plenary indulgence &amp; acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance from ſin, and her reward, death: for death is the wages and ſtipend of ſinne. Is not this a tyrannie going far beyond that of <hi>Nero,</hi> ſurpaſsing that of <hi>Decius,</hi> and an hundred times more execrable than that of <hi>Heliogabalus?</hi> Theſe men can ſuffer him whom they haue ſeene with their eyes die in a ken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell, ſtabbing and ſtabbed in a drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken humour; or him, who all his life time hath played the throat-cutting Ruffian, or the leacherous whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monger, and who at laſt hath dyed in the Poxe, without ſo much as <hi>poenitendi animus;</hi> yea, him, whom they haue heard with their eares awake <hi>Stix, Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the,</hi> and <hi>Acheron</hi> with hideous and fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full bannings, abuſe with thunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolts, and cannon-ſhot volies of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominable oathes the great and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Name of the euerliuing God: ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:16551:13"/>
men (I ſay) they can indure to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tombed &amp; incoffined with them, and to haue their portion in their ground, and to lie among them with abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of peace, whereas they would ſtriue to ranſacke Heauen and Earth; yea, <hi>Acheronta mouerent;</hi> they would euen trouble Hell it ſelfe, if they did know that any Proteſtants aſhes did reſt there. O Lord, how long wilt thou delay, and ſuffer this vnheard of cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie? To returne to my purpoſe. The reaſon of all theſe things, is either the want of charitie, or of prudent diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of things neceſſary from things indifferent. This age is peſtered, yea, it is conſumed with theſe fire-brands in matters indefinable. Many good Chriſtian people haue vſed direct and indirect meanes to cure this ſore, to quench theſe faggots with their Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings full of prudence and pietie; but behold their reward, both the parties haue perſecuted them with calumnies,
<pb facs="tcp:16551:14"/>
calling them Neutralls, neither <hi>hic,</hi> nor <hi>haec,</hi> Nullifidians, Vbiquitaries: yea, the ordinary cenſure goeth ſo far, as with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſoule and conſcience now to call them Atheiſts; Or elſe both the parties hate them in ſuch a meaſure, that they thruſt them from their Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. This maketh the Speakers in this buſineſſe to bee few, but Writers almoſt none.</p>
            <p>I remember that conferring with a learned man concerning this ſubiect, I asked him why he did not write his iudgement in theſe controuerſies. His anſwer was, <hi>Cui vſui reip. Chriſtianae, et cui bono mihi?</hi> telling me, that it could not helpe the generall cauſe one whit, but doe much hurt to the doer. I know many ſuch on both ſides, who lament the Schiſme, and yet cannot helpe it. Oh that the Roman Church, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the beautifulleſt amongſt wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, that faireſt and moſt gliſtering Church amongſt all her Siſters milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant
<pb facs="tcp:16551:14"/>
vpon Earth, would acknowledge her ſelfe to be a Siſter and not a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris. There was a time when ſhe gaue her helping hand, (as at the famous Councells of <hi>Nice, Epheſus, Constanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople,</hi> and <hi>Chalcedon</hi>) and did not rule with a dictatory power. There was a time, when in an harmonicall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord ſhe was moued with the reſt of her planeticall and wandring Siſters in this vaile of ſorrow and triall, by the reuolution of her firſt mouer, and did ſhine amongſt them all like <hi>Phoebus</hi> in his Spheare; imparting out of her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion and charytie that portion of light, which her Redeemer had made her Hand-maide of euen then, when <hi>Arrianiſme</hi> had ouer-runne all the <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rient</hi> and <hi>Affrick,</hi> when <hi>Ierome</hi> cried out of it, <hi>Ingemuit mundus ſe Arrianum eſſe factum;</hi> but now the fogge of her ſmoakie vapours obſcureth the decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning rayes of Religion and Charity, which in the latter ages are ſo faſt
<pb facs="tcp:16551:15"/>
ruſhing to their Sun-ſet, yea to their lamentable and darkeſome midnight. Alas, who ſhall furniſh my eyes with floods of waters? &amp; who ſhall make my head a liuing ſpring, that from henceforth I may water my Couch with ſorrowfull teares? Let mee mourne with the Turtle, and chatter with the Crow, for the loſſe of my beloued: Hee is gone and left his people to their own fancies and luna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke toyes. Our ſinnes haue baniſhed him; let repentance recall him. Cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in faith hath loſt him; let feruen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie find him. Vnſetled hope could not keepe him; let ſteadfaſtneſſe lay hold on him. Periurie, Swearing, Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, Idoll-worſhip, haue ſhut the doore of our ſoules vpon him: Let feare, reuerence, with regard of his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall Maieſtie and illimited power open againe vnto him. Contempt of his Sabbath made him loath vs; fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenting his Sanctuary will force him
<pb facs="tcp:16551:15"/>
to loue vs Miſ-regard of Superiours, Parents, &amp; Magiſtrates, hath made vs Tutorleſſe; obedience to our Prince, loue to our Magiſtrates, regard to Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, will make him haue a care of vs. Lying, Slaunderous Callumnies, Backbiting our Neighbours, haue made him ſuffer theſe inteſtine Iarres in Religion and worſhip; loue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards our Brethren will make him reunite our affections in one.</p>
            <p>This Treatiſe of differences I col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, partly by reading partly by the helpe of ſome acquaintance of mine tenne yeares agoe in the <hi>Low-Countries. Petrus van Heiffen</hi> (one of my owne profeſsion) at my requeſt collected all he could finde by his reading in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate, and ſearching of Libraries; <hi>Iekan Heymer</hi> (a Papiſt) by his trauailes to <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> helped me with the oddeſt peeces he could finde, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing alſo trauailed in the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories, where by conferring with
<pb facs="tcp:16551:16"/>
ſome <hi>Grecians,</hi> he got moſt ſure intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence of their opinions. Theſe ſcrowles I kept theſe tenne yeares, to ſee if any other had handled this Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect before in the Engliſh tongue; and hauing found by diligent enquirie and ſcruteny, that no man heretofore hath touched this matter in this tongue, I thought good (Chriſtian brother) to let thee ſmell theſe differences, that perceiuing the ſtinking ſtreames which runne from theſe impure and muddy Springs, thou maiſt learne to haue a care of thy ſelfe. <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> taught Sophiſticall captions, not that his Schollers ſhould practiſe Sophiſtry, but that they ſhould be able to repell it. The <hi>Perſians</hi> were wont to paint a whore with one hand in the young<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans pocket, and with the other hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a knife to cut his throat; not that their youths ſhould frequent the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of naughty and lewd women, but that they ſhould ſeek by all meanes
<pb facs="tcp:16551:16"/>
poſsible to ſhun them and their dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable tricks. <hi>O how ioyfull a thing is it to ſee brethren hold faſt the bond of friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and amity.</hi> If a man would but behold theſe Controuerſies as a neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trall only, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould he plainly ſee the errours of both ſides, where as ſpleene and choller doth hinder any man in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged on either ſide from ſearching the truth. The <hi>Turkes</hi> in their damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable <hi>Mahumetan</hi> worſhip, the <hi>Pagans</hi> in worſhipping the Sunne &amp; Moone, the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> in their <hi>Iſis</hi> and <hi>Oſyris,</hi> the <hi>Numidians, Lybians,</hi> in their ſeruing of cats, dogges, onyons and leekes, vſe diuerſitie of Ceremonies and Rites; yet they ſtill retaine the<note n="*" place="margin">Becauſe there is no good bond of friend<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhip but that which is grounded vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on God and his worſhip.</note> ill-tied knot of friendſhip in their Idol-ſeruice. But Chriſtians thunder calumnies and bolt excommunications one againſt another, if there be but a difference in any kinde of Ceremonies. Chriſtian brethren, this maketh thoſe that are without to be ſcandalized by vs Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,
<pb facs="tcp:16551:17"/>
to loath our profeſsion, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne our faith, to perſecute our per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, to ouerthrow our Kingdomes, to ſpoyle our Countries, to depriue vs of our liberties and priuiledges, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force many weake ones to imbrace I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrie, to torture the conſtant with intolerable, yea vnexpreſſable torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, to the end they may make them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce Chriſtianitie; yea, which is worſt of all, they by our diuiſions, are kindled with ſuch hatred againſt vs, and with ſuch zeale to their owne profeſsion, that they thinke they doe God good ſeruice, and a great benefit to poore ſoules, when they make them abiure their faith and baptiſme. O mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable Chriſtians! returne, returne vnto the Lord, for you haue falne by your iniquities, returne (I ſay) vnto him, and he will cure you of your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iquities. Earneſt prayer, endleſſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion, volumes of mourning Madri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>galls, like <hi>Dauids</hi> Penitentialls, clouds
<pb facs="tcp:16551:17"/>
of watry ſighs; <hi>Nineuies</hi> faſting, <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſes</hi> repenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, <hi>Peters</hi> weeping, with <hi>Pauls</hi> reformation, is the ſole Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thridaticke, the ſoueraigne <hi>Pandoron,</hi> the true <hi>Alexipharmacon,</hi> the pureſt ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, the rareſt compound that can o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen this vlcer, ranſacke this botch, and cure this incurable, and neuer enough to be lamented diſſeaſe of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an world. <hi>O vtinam tantum facerent qui poſſunt, quantum volo qui nil valeo,</hi> Would to God the Potentates &amp; Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchs of the Earth (the Kings and Princes I meane of Chriſtendome) would ioyne hand in hand to build the walls of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> to raiſe vp the Towers of <hi>Sion.</hi> O where is there a <hi>Zorobabel</hi> to re-edefie the walles of the old Temple? the Temple had a <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> to build her, a <hi>Zorobabel</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>build her, though not ſo ſumptuous as ſhe was at firſt, yet in great pompe and glory.</p>
            <p>I ſue for no new <hi>Salomon:</hi> there
<pb facs="tcp:16551:18"/>
muſt be but one, euen he who foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his Church with his blood, the Lambe of God, <hi>Mactatus à iactus mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di fundamentis,</hi> the Prince of peace, the Authour of loue; yet we may haue, yea, we haue preſently many <hi>Zoroba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels,</hi> many Maſters of worke in the Chriſtian world: ſome Greekiſh, ſome Latine, and ſome Reformed; ſome Ruſsian, ſome Armenian, ſome Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian, ſome Abiſsine; euery one accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the meaſure of his iudgement and Learning, would helpe to repaire thoſe Breaches. And that this may be effected, you ſacred Monarchs vſe your authoritie, you nurſing Fathers, cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſe with the rod where there is need of the ſame: Cut away with the Sword of Iuſtice, (which you carry not in vaine) the trunkes of Pride, Vaine-glory, and Selfe-loue, which ouer-whelme the Clergie for the moſt part: Learned Schoole men, leaue the brainſicke and fooliſh inventions of
<pb facs="tcp:16551:18"/>
               <hi>Ariſtotle, Philoponus, Themiſtius Aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roes,</hi> leaue (I ſay) to mingle them with the pure and liuing Chriſtall Springs of the Word. Writers of Controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies hunt not after Victory ambitiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>vbi lis eſt de lana caprina,</hi> for the moſt part: But ſearch Truth, <hi>ſincero, &amp; animo candido,</hi> knowing that your account ſhall be great before God, if you leade the poore ignorant to fall in the ditch. And this I ſay not ſo much for any danger that is in any moderne opinion, but in reſpect of the great and dangerous ſcandall, whereby wee offend the weake and tender Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of the poore and ignorant Lai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, which ſolemnely ſweareth (being ſo by vs informed) that euery poynt of Controuerſie is either an Article of a new Creed, or elſe a new Article ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the Creed; and the Laitie erring in Iudgement, doe thunder all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary minds to hell for euer. And ſo the ſinne of the people is not ſo much
<pb facs="tcp:16551:19"/>
an errour of beleefe, (though muzled vp like blind bayards in ignorance, and implicite faith) as it is the defect of charitie towards their brethren, which is the greateſt ſinne a man can commit againſt his Neighbour: yea, it maketh a man hard in his Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and without repentance, and therefore damnable.</p>
            <p>I remember, that once conferring with a Couſin of mine, a prudent and learned Gentleman, compleat in all endowments of body and mind, (his want of charitie onely being excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) he ſaid, Woe is mee, that you ſhould be in Hell, when I am in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, ſeeing you are an Heretike, (Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant he meant) I anſwered, Well Sir, you are too raſh in iudging. I am as ſure (ſaid hee) of your damnation, if you die a Proteſtant, as that Chriſt is in heauen at the right hand of the Father. I anſwered, You that are Papiſts are very ſure of our damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb facs="tcp:16551:19"/>
I wonder greatly, that your are neuer ſure of your owne ſaluation: But thus much I tell you, I will not ſit vpon Gods Tribunall, to giue out the Sentence of condemnation againſt you; yet ſince you lacke charitie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards me your Chriſtian Brother, and giue out the ſentence of condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt me ſo peremptorily, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Gods part vpon you: I thinke you will be damned, except you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent you of your ſpeech. And take not my Iudgement for raſh, ſince I iudge the Tree by the Fruit, and you by your Charitie, which is the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall and cardinall Vertue of the law. Deuout Preachers, fill your Sermons from the Store-houſe of Scripture: informe in faith from Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Romanes,</hi> and from the firſt and ſecond of <hi>Iames:</hi> reforme manners from <hi>Ieremie, Ezechiell, Hoſea,</hi> and <hi>Ioel:</hi> denounce iudgements from <hi>Zacharia, Amos, Ionas, Michaiah:</hi> teach your
<pb facs="tcp:16551:20"/>
ſelues from <hi>Titus,</hi> and <hi>Timothie.</hi> This is all your taske, and to liue well, and goe before the people like the fierie Pillar in the night, and the Cloud in the day, to guide them, and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue them from Schiſme and Hereſie. Doe not ſpend your time in inventing Rhethoricke to admiration, critticke Methods for emulation, vnprofitable Queſtions breeding Controuerſies: Feed not the itching eares of the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous people with Nouelties, need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe queſtions, and vnhandſomely borrowed Similies. In touching and taxing your Aduerſaries in Pulpits, (which would to God you did more ſeldome) doe not ſo much endeauour to make them odious to your people, as to make your hearers commiſerate their eſtate, for whom Chriſt died; and to mooue your Auditorie to pray for their converſion, and not for their confuſion. Our prayer to God ſhould be to ſuſpend his Iudgements,
<pb facs="tcp:16551:20"/>
and to helpe vs with grace, as he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to giue it for meaſure, and when hee pleaſeth to giue it for time. Prayer ſhould bee Optatiue, deſiring and wiſhing with feare and humilitie, no wayes Imperatiue, enioyning ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and circumſtance to God, that he would inflict ſuch puniſhment, at ſuch time, and in ſuch place, vpon ſuch and ſuch perſons. Popiſh curſes and Exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munications, (the Sword which vntie the Gordian knot of the Church, the Hammer which broake the wall in the mids, the noyſe which muſt not be heard at the rebuilding of the Temple.) I abhorre with my ſoule, ſince the peremptory and raſh Excommunications, the drawing of the Sword of God vpon euery idle oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion ſcandalouſly, and many times in deriſion of God and his Church, the cutting off men from the Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for little cauſes, for no cauſes; yea for vertuous actions, and reproouing
<pb facs="tcp:16551:21"/>
of ſinnes offenſiue to God, and oppro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brious to man, haue occaſioned, bred, brought to light, nouriſhed, and yet ſtill foſter the rent of the Church. Lord giue vs affections to loue peace, hearts to bewaile the Schiſme, and then will we hope for Vnion. Which (O Lord) in thy due time performe to thy glory, the honour of thy Sonne, and the comfort of thoſe who ſhall perſeuere in thy grace to the end. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine in the Lord,</hi> I. R.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:16551:21"/>
            <head>THE DIFFERENCES BETWEENE THE Eaſterne and Weſterne CHVRCHES.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He cauſes of this lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Schiſme, which diuided the affections of Chriſtians, and brought vpon them the yoake of Turkiſh ſeruitude, as I can gather them from <hi>Petrus Stewartius Leodius,</hi> (a man by diſcent of the Scottiſh blood, for Religion a Romiſh Catholicke, remarkable for his dignity, Vice-Chauncelour, and profeſſor of Diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in <hi>Ingolſtade</hi> famous for the Ieſuites
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:16551:22"/>
renowned Schoole there) neither adding, nor diminiſhing from his words (as they are ſet downe in his notes vpon <hi>Caleca,</hi> who being a <hi>Greeke,</hi> wrote againſt the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rientall Churches in defence of the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of the Occidentall Churches) you ſhall haue faithfully tranſlated, as here fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
            <div type="articles">
               <head>Petrus Stewartius in Calecam Pag. 407. editione Ingolſtadi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enſi 1608. <hi>Ex varijs Graeco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum monumentis.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WE think that the cauſes, or rather the excuſes of the Schiſme, are foure.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt, the deuiſion of the Empire: for albeit the Emperours who did raigne at <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople,</hi> after <hi>Conſtantines</hi> departure from the Citie of <hi>Rome</hi> (<note n="a" place="margin">He touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the forged donation of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> which I would wiſh no man to beleeue, ſince it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed inuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cibly by the learned of this Age. <hi>Reynolds</hi> with <hi>Hart.</hi> Hiſtory of <hi>Magdenburge,</hi> and the Booke intituled <hi>Conſtantines</hi> defence.</note> becauſe they had by a donation beſtowed it all, (as wee ſpake be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) vpon the Church) had not right it <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> yet not withſtanding ſometimes they ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:16551:22"/>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">This indeed is not probable that they had no right at all in Rome, and yet ſhould rule euery where. Iudge indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Reader.</note> euery where. But when a barbarous Nation had ruſhed<note n="c" place="margin">Infra pro in videtur poni.</note> into <hi>Italy,</hi> euen to <hi>Rome,</hi> and the<note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Loe.</hi> 3.</note> Pope had required the aide of <hi>Leo</hi> Emperour then at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> who negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently refuſed aide to the Church, the Pope was forced to recall<note n="e" place="margin">Anno Dom. <hi>800.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Charles-maine</hi> from the French Territories, and make him Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour in <hi>Italy,</hi> and defender of the Church: For this Pope <hi>Leo</hi> was a man much giuen to voluptuouſneſſe, (as we read) and therefore too too remiſſe in his gouernement of the Empire, whence it came to paſſe, that in his time the <hi>Sarazens</hi> tooke <hi>Syria,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Turks, Capadocia;</hi> and ſo the Roman Empire was diuided.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſecond cauſe of the deuiſion was, becauſe they were not called to the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell<note n="f" place="margin">Vltra mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanum ſeu Lugdunenſe lib. Greg. x.</note> beyond the hills, when the word (<hi>filio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que,</hi> and from the ſonne) was added.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The third occaſion was (which they themſelues ſometimes in familiar conference did ſhew vnto vs) the too great and extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary exaction of the Popes Legats; for when they brought yearely the Chriſme from the Apoſtolicke Sea to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> they would not depart from thence, vnleſſe they had eighty pound weight of gold, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides other gifts beſtowed vpon them. I will be ſilent of the pompe and pride (whereof they ſpake) which the Legats ſhew there.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The fourth and chiefeſt cauſe vpon the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:16551:23"/>
Clergies part was the depoſition of their Patriarch <hi>Photius,</hi>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>Et</hi> in the Latine multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied ſoundeth harſhly.</note> the excommunicating of him with other Prelats and ſome Abbots.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paulo infra.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe things were written in <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople,</hi> by the preaching Friers for the edify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the people and for the profiting of ſoules, in the yeare of our Lord 1252. to the praiſe and glory of the Father, Sonne, and Holy Ghoſt. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="controversion">
               <head>The Articles controuerted.</head>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The proceſsion of the Holy-Ghoſt not only from the Father, but from the Sonne alſo, of which <hi>Caleca</hi> writeth copiouſly in his firſt three Bookes.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond Controuerſie is the addition of the word (<hi>filióque</hi> and from the Sonne) to the Creede.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third is vnleauened bread, vſed in the Euchariſt for leauened; for the Eaſterne Churches ſay that Chriſt vſed leauened Bread.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> The fourth is the bleſſed eſtate of the Saints, and damnation of the wicked; for the Grecians hold, that though ſoules are fully clenſed and purged from ſinne in this life, yet they inioy not their bleſſedneſſe in an inſtant after they part from the body, but
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:16551:23"/>
that they are ſuſpended vntill the day of ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall reſurrection: So they hold that the ſoules of Reprobates which die in their ſins without repentance, are not tormented in the higheſt meaſure before the day of Doome.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> The fift is Purgatory, concerning which point the Grecians wrote a Booke, which now is tranſlated into Latin, and ſet out by a Proteſtant writer <hi>Vulcanius,</hi> in which they refute Purgatory, and anſwer to the Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of Scripture and Fathers obiected a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them for the defence of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> The ſixt is, becauſe in the Latine Church a Prieſt will execute the Office of a Deacon, for the Grecians hold it vnlawfull, that any man except he be a Deacon read their Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, or common ſeruice, (which the Latins call Maſſe) whereas the Latin Church will ſuffer a Prieſt to doe the Office of a Deacon, ſeeing that a Church man is ordained Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con before he be Prieſt; and the taking vpon him the Order of Prieſt-hood, which is a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour degree, excludeth not the inferiour degree of Deaconſhip, which he had before. Now the Office of a Deacon is to giue the Cup to the Prieſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> The ſeuenth is Images, which the Greeke Church doth not worſhip as the Latine doth: for in the dayes of <hi>Leo Iſaurus,</hi> called by others, <hi>Iconomachus</hi> (becauſe he deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:16551:24"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:16551:24"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:16551:25"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:16551:25"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:16551:26"/>
Images) the Councell holden at <hi>Epheſus</hi> did condemne Image-worſhip; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after followed the breaking of them in pieces after a rude and ſcandalous manner indeed, for which <hi>Gregorius</hi> 2. did excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate <hi>Leo</hi> and all his adherents, <hi>anno</hi> 716. and did free the Subiects of <hi>Leo</hi> from their oath of Obedience; which as<note n="*" place="margin">In Epitoma Hiſtoriarum.</note> 
                  <hi>Turſelme</hi> the Ieſuite relateth, made the Romanes, with thoſe of <hi>Pentapolis, Rauenna,</hi> and <hi>Campania,</hi> to reiect <hi>Leo</hi> their Emperour, and to rebell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him. The Pope in a Councell at <hi>Rome</hi> decreed, That Images ſhould bee kept to helpe the rude multitude, and to be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped by them, who could not reade Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. And ſo the Pope and the Emperour running vpon two extremities; the one too extreame in defacing and demoliſhing the Images barbarouſly; the other in erecting and honouring them too much. The Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell aſſembled at <hi>Franckford,</hi> which did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt of Germane, Engliſh, French, and Italian Biſhops, condemned the breaking and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facing of Images, and reiected the worſhip of them, by reaſon of the Canon of the Councell of <hi>Eliberis, Ne quod colitur in pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietibus pingatur,</hi> Let not that be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped which is painted on walls. And heere I muſt adde the words of <hi>Carolus, lib.</hi> 4. <hi>contra Graecorum Synodum, Cap.</hi> 9. <hi>Imagines nil ſi non habentur derogant, nil ſi habentur praerogant,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:16551:26"/>
cum tamen abdicatae quandam incautam leuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem afferant, adoratae vero culpam inurant:</hi> Images derogate nothing from Chriſtianitie if they bee not at all; they helpe it nothing if they bee; but to reiect them raſhly, it ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gueth a certaine fooliſh lightneſſe; and the worſhipping of them doth make men faultie. But that famous Writer, <hi>G. Caſſander lib. Conſult. cap. de Imaginibus,</hi> ſheweth, that in the dayes next the Apoſtolicke times, for many ages, there was no vſe of Images in the Baſilickes and Churches. But to ſpeake of the opinion of the Grecians now adayes concerning Images, the Controuerſie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene them and the Romiſh Church ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in two poynts.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The Grecians will admit no Image of
Chriſt and the Saints, if it bee molten, or grauen, thinking it directly forbidden in the ſecond Commandement: but if it be painted, then they like of it.</p>
               <p>This diſtinction the Latines hold to bee fooliſh, ſaying, That the Grecians may as well gather out of that Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement, that there ſhould be no Pictures of Chriſt or the Saints, Seeing that the Commaundement ſayeth, Thou ſhall not make to thy ſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny grauen Image, nor the ſimilitude of any thing that is in heauen aboue, nor in the earth beneath, nor in the waters vnder the earth. <hi>Poſſevinus in ſua Muſcouia,</hi> writeth
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:16551:27"/>
thus, and ſheweth that the <hi>Rutheni</hi> worſhip the Images of Chriſt and Saints, when they are painted.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The Grecians will worſhip no Image; yea, they will admit no Image (ſo many, to wit, of the Grecians as allow of Image-worſhip, which are the <hi>Rutheni</hi>) but that which hath the Name of Chriſt and the Saints deſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Image, the Type, <hi>viz.</hi> carrying the name of the Prototype. And if the name of Chriſt be written in Greeke letters, they like the Picture; if in Latine, they reiect it. Of thoſe <hi>Poſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>vinus, Ibidem. Quod Rutheni tui mirantur, &amp;c.</hi> Whereas the Ruſſians won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that wee adde not the names to the Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, as they doe. Vnderſtand thou, that if the addition of the names be onely neceſſary that the Saints may bee knowen, then the names are not needfull to thoſe that know the Images without names, &amp;c. And if they will ſay that in the very name there is ſome vertue, thou ſhalt doe well not to conceiue any vertue to bee in theſe notes; but that in a liuely faith onely ſtandeth all the vigour and ſtrength of this buſineſſe, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> The eighth difference is this, The La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines in making the ſigne of the Croſſe vpon themſelues, begin at the right hand: but the Grecians are contrary to them, for they begin at the left hand; but when the Greci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans make the ſigne of the Croſſe vpon any
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:16551:27"/>
other, then they begin at the right hand, as <hi>Caleca</hi> writeth, <hi>Lib.</hi> 4. <hi>de Crucis ſigno,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he plainely wondreth, and ſheweth the wondring of ſome of the Latines at the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall humour of the Grecians, who would haue rent the Vnitie of the Church for ſuch an indifferent poynt of Ceremonie, as for making the Signe, either this way, or that way.</p>
               <p>It may be demaunded,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Obiect.</hi> 1.</note> Why the reformed Churches reiect the vſe of the Croſſe, and refuſe to carry it about their neckes, and to make the ſigne of it daily vpon their bodies, ſeeing that both the Latine Church, and a great part of the Greekiſh Church vſe the ſame frequently, eſpecially the Ruſſians, which in this Ceremonie are become (par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don the word) ſuperſubſtantiall, and fooliſh in vſing of it.</p>
               <p>I anſwere,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> That as the Croſſe was one of the Inſtruments of mans ſaluation, in the eye of the world it was diſgracefull and odious; ſo that Iewes, Pagans, and Infidels did ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect it to Chriſtians as a matter of infamy, and made the ſigne thereof in deriſion of Chriſtianitie; Chriſtians therefore to ſhew that they were not aſhamed of Chriſts death, or of the manner of it, they vſed the ſigne of it in their actions and doings, both in their religious Seruice, and in any ciuill buſineſſe. In the Warres they carried the Croſſe vpon
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:16551:28"/>
their breaſts, or about their necks; the Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard of Chriſtians oftentimes was made in forme of a Croſſe, and now ſeeing that the Grecians are daily conuerſant with <hi>Mahu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metans, Infidells</hi> and others, who neuer ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged Chriſt as the Meſsias; but mocke Chriſtians for beleeuing in one who was hanged vpon a Croſſe: the moderate vſe of the ſigne with the carrying of it about their necks or after any other manner cannot be rebuked. As for the Proteſtant and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches, there is no ſuch neceſsity of wearing it and vſing it on all occaſions, ſeing they dwell amongſt Chriſtians, who take no exceptions at the manner of Chriſts death: as for thoſe of the Roman Church, they haue thought it (being of it ſelfe a meere indifferent thing) ſo neceſſary in all their religious duties, that they haue too too much abuſed it, holding almoſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſanctified but that which is clogged and ouer-burdened (that I may ſay ſo) with croſsing. Therefore Proteſtants to ſhun the inconuenience vpon the popiſh ſide, and not hauing occaſion of the other motiues vpon the Greatians ſide, they preſſe not the people with this Ceremonie: though after baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, as an auncient cuſtome deriued from the Primitiue Ages in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> they vſe the Signe of the Croſſe; and that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Baptiſme, (I ſay) the Roman Church ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:16551:28"/>
it before it, to ſhew that they put no vertue in the ſigne to baniſh Deuills out of the body or ſoule of the Child, as Popiſh Prieſts doe; but only vſe it as a decent and religious cuſtome, when the Child is ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and cleanſed by the water of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> The ninth Article, is faſting vpon Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, called <hi>ieiunium ſabbati,</hi> of which Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall <hi>Baronius, Anno Chriſti</hi> 57. <hi>numero.</hi> 202. diſputeth after this manner: The ſumme of whoſe ſpeeches being conferred with other writers of that kind, is this.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Baronius. Vetus eſt illa quaeſtio, &amp;c.</hi> That is an auncient queſtion (of which <hi>Hierom.</hi> to <hi>Lucinius</hi>) concerning which, <hi>Thippolitus</hi> Martyre, and many famous Writers ſet out their Commentaries: to wit, wherefore Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turday ſhould be added to the Faſts in the Weſterne Churches: on which if a man faſt in the Orientall Churches hee is accounted execrable, and it hath beene ſo in the Orient from the very beginning of Chriſtianity, as <hi>Ignatius</hi> writing to the <hi>Philippians</hi> ſheweth, <hi>Si quis dominicum diem &amp;c.</hi> If any man faſt on Sunday or on the Sabbath (<note n="*" place="margin">Saturday be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Eaſter, for Chriſts lying in the graue that day.</note> one being ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted) he is a murderer of Chriſt. Againe, there is an Apoſtolicke Canon concerning the ſame, <hi>Can.</hi> 65. and repeated in the 6. <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Which <hi>Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> holdeth to be a baſtard Canon.</note> 
                  <hi>Can.</hi> 55. The reaſon wherefore <hi>Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> did hold it to be ſuch an execrable crime
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:16551:29"/>
was this: two ſortes of Hereticks were mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues and cauſes of it; the firſt were thoſe who denied Chriſts reſurrection, and ſo when Chriſtians reioyced on the Lords day, thoſe Heretickes paſſed it ouer in mourning and faſting.</p>
               <p>The ſecond were thoſe, which affirmed that the God of the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> who made the World and the Law, was euill, and that Chriſt came to deſtroy the Law. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that the God of the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> reſted the ſeauenth day, and the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> did honour God, and keepe that day becauſe of his or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, as a feaſtiuall and not a faſting day: therefore theſe Heretickes, in diſgrace of the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> God, and their Sabbath, did faſt and not feaſt on it. <hi>Simon Magus</hi> was Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour of this hereſie: <hi>Menander, Saturninus, Baſilides, Cerinthus</hi> &amp; <hi>Carpocrates,</hi> were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders of it, of which <hi>Irenaeus, Epipha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All theſe liued with <hi>Ignatius,</hi> hee wrot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them and hated the Ceremony for the Hereticks vſe of it: <hi>Cerdon</hi> and <hi>Marcion</hi> followed this point. And though theſe He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retickes had many differing errours, yet they all agreed in this, that they made God the Creator, authour of euill, and contumeliouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly faſted on that day; as it were, to oppoſe themſelues to his conſtitution. This was the reaſon that not only they abſtained in the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rient
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:16551:29"/>
from faſting on Saturdayes, becauſe Hereticks did faſt on thoſe daies; but alſo they vſed to ſpend the day in great cheereful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: and they aſſemble themſelues vnto their holy exerciſes, as frequent on the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turday, as on the Lords day. Many of the auncients beare witneſſe to this, eſpecially <hi>Clement,</hi> who in the Apoſtolicke conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſaith,<note place="margin">Which booke of his is iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions.</note> 
                  <hi>Sabatum &amp; dominicum diem feſtum agimus, &amp;c.</hi> We make both the Saturday and the Sunday holy-daies: becauſe the firſt is a monument of Natures accompliſhment; the ſecond of Chriſts reſurrection. Wee keepe our Sabbath in the yeare on which we faſt and not feaſt, for our Lords buriall, &amp;c. Thus <hi>Clement,</hi> with whom agree <hi>Socrates, Gregorius, N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſſenus, Anaſtaſius, Nicaenus;</hi> And this the Orient did out of religious hearts and full of piety, in oppoſition to He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie, and not in a Iudaizing humour.</p>
               <p>The reaſon wherfore the Weſterne Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches faſt on Saturday, is firſt,<note place="margin">If that ſtory of that diſputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on be not fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulous.</note> as S. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> to <hi>Caſulanus</hi> writeth, becauſe that <hi>Peter</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vpon the Lords day to diſpute with <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Magus,</hi> on the Saturday before he faſted with the whole Church; and therefore for the proſperous ſucceſſe which <hi>Peter</hi> had in that buſineſſe, the Occidentall Churches e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſince honoured that day with faſting.</p>
               <p>The ſecond reaſon, which is more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, is the reaſon of Pope <hi>Innocentius</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:16551:30"/>
to <hi>Decentius Eugubinus</hi> Biſhop, which is, that becauſe Saturday was a time wherein the Diſciples, and the bleſſed Virgin, faſted and mourned for our bleſſed Sauiour whilſt he was in the graue: therefore as the fourth day being Wedneſday, and the ſixt being Friday, were conſecrated to faſting by the Weſterne Churches: ſo likewiſe in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of our Sauiours abode in the graue, they appointed Saturday to bee a faſting day.</p>
               <p>Therefore <hi>Barnious</hi> deſireth, that no man ſhould take exception againſt the cuſtome of the Latin Church, in which the former here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies did not ariſe, for which ſhe needed not to forbare her faſting dayes, not being troubled with any ſuch Hereticks; and which did not condemne but rather iuſtified the Greekiſh Church for keeping no company with Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks in this point.</p>
               <p>The tenth Controuerſie, is becauſe the Latins are not ſo ſtrict in their faſting, when they doe faſt, neither faſt they ſo frequently as the Grecians doe. The heads of this tenth Controuerſie are reduced to eight branches, as they are rehearſed and gathered by ſundry men out of the <hi>Bauarian</hi> bibliothecke in the Index, which is called <hi>Index errorum Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae Eccleſiae olim Conſtantinopoli gracè ſcripta nunc Latinè per &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:16551:30"/>The firſt branch of Hereſie laid to the charge of the Latin Church, is becauſe the Latins doe not obſerue the chiefe eating weeke (called <hi>Hebdomas</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) but in that weeke eate fleſh, as alſo on two daies of the firſt weeke of Lent. They begin their faſting vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the fourth day of the weeke, (called Wedneſday by vs) giuing a reaſon, forſooth, becauſe from this day of the firſt weeke, to the weeke of Palmes the fortie daies are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed; ſo ſtrict are theſe faſters in keeping exactly the number of fortie.</p>
               <p>The ſecond branch is, becauſe the Latins once a day quickly eating, at night they eate fiſh their bellies full, and ſome bcome drunke; and they make no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to drinke all the day long; and yet with this one refreſhment of theirs, they will haue their faſt vnblamable and vnreprehenſibly kept.</p>
               <p>The third is, becauſe on euery Saturday and Lords day of the Lent, they giue their children cheeſe and egges to eate, &amp; they themſelues eate the ſame with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any ſcruple at all vpon the fiſh day of the great Feaſtiuitie, that is, vpon holy Thurſday.</p>
               <p>The fourth is, becauſe all the yeare long vpon any fourth or ſixt day, they eate either fiſh or fleſh; all eate fleſh vpon
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:16551:31"/>
the fourth day, ſome alſo vpon the ſixt.</p>
               <p>The fift, as they faſt euery ſixt day eating at night, ſo though the day of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuity or Circumſition, or any of the great Feaſts fall vpon Saturday, they will not loſe the Faſt for it.</p>
               <p>The ſixt, they eate with dogges and tame beares, to which they throw the plat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and diſhes that they may lick them, out of which, they themſelues after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards eate meat.</p>
               <p>The ſeuenth, their Monkes eate fat of Hogges growing faſt to the fleſh, which is called Lard, &amp; vpon any ſuſpicion of ſicknes (though it be neuer ſo little) both Monks and Laicks eate fleſh in the Lent. But if it fall out that any Monke be ordained a Biſhop, then ſafely with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any controulement hee eateth fleſh.</p>
               <p>The eight, the Latins are not vniforme in their faſting in the Lent time, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, faſt 9. weekes: the Italians 6. others 8. others fewer.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> The eleuenth Article is the Popes<note n="*" place="margin">Sentina ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum eſt.</note> ſupre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macie; the Romiſh Church challengeth Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacie to the Pope from <hi>Peter</hi> by all Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall Canons, as ſhe alleadgeth. The Grecians ſtrongly deny all the allegations of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:16551:31"/>
the Latin Churches, and leaning to the fourth generall Synod at <hi>Chalcedon;</hi> at laſt they attribute the Superiority to Sea of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople,</hi> &amp; that by two Canons, in which it is ſaid, if controuerſies cannot bee ended by Biſhops in Prouinciall, or Nationall Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nods, then<note n="*" place="margin">Ibi termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nentur. Can. <hi>9.</hi>
                  </note> let them bee determined by the Biſhop of the Princely Citie <hi>Constantinople.</hi> This is repeated againe in the ſame Synod in another Canon, and therefore I will here ſet downe the words of <hi>Hugo Aetherianus,</hi> who deliuereth the Grecians mind after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. <hi>Romanus Pontifex, &amp; omnes partium occi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentalium Chriſtiani ſacerdotes &amp; Laici praeter Calabros, ante multa tempora extra Catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam Eccleſiam peruagantur, Euangelicarum &amp; Apoſtolicarum traditionum ignari &amp; a fide ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eni.</hi> The Roman Biſhop, and all the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Prieſts of the Weſterne parts and Laicks, except the <hi>Calabrians,</hi> this long time haue gone aſtray from the Catholicke Church, being ignorant of the Euangelicall and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolicke troditions, and Aliens from the faith. And a little after, <hi>Etinim ſua concimantes &amp; alienis adhaerentes, neque diuinis Scripturis re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darguentibus ipſorum errores, neque illis qui ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſos miſerunt volunt morem gerere,</hi> for making vp their owne conceits, and adhering to ſtrange opinions, they will neither obey the Scripture rebuking their errour, nor yet thoſe men who ordained them.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:16551:32"/>The Princes of their Prieſts goe to warre with Laicks in Armes, and they fight in the Battell marching before others.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ex iudice de miſſae ſacrificio in Bibliotheca Bauarica,</hi> wee finde theſe notes gathered by <hi>Petrus Stewartius</hi> as errours of Grecians, and yet imputing them to the Latins: but how iuſtly, let the Reader iudge, ſeeing my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent goeth no farther then to tranſlate the words without any gloſſe or cenſure of mine.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Titulo</hi> 5.<note n="*" place="margin">This is more than truly al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged againſt the Church of Rome which forbiddeth reading of Scripture.</note> 
                  <hi>Sacros canones &amp; Sacras Literas &amp;c.</hi> Scarce read they the ſacred rules and holy Scriptures; they ſay, that the Popes Commandements, who for the time ſitteth in the Sea of Rome, are their Canons and Lawes. They hold that the precepts of thoſe who are dead, whether Apoſtles or Fathers, are dead with them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tittulo</hi> 7. They make not much account of periury; yea, the Pope freeth them of all periurie, whenſoeuer they intend to breake any bargaine or couenant made with any man.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Titulo</hi> 30. The Pope and his Prieſtly traine remit ſlaughter, periurie, and all kinde of crimes paſt, or to come, by which remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion there is a gate opened to all ſort of villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. And that which is moſt fooliſh and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous, for the future time, they will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to a prefined &amp; determinated time of two
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:16551:32"/>
three, more or fewer months or yeares. They ſport after the ſame manner with by-paſt of fences, forgiuing the ſinnes of dayes, months, or yeares: And yet they cannot tell by what authority, and vpon what grounds, or by what Eccleſiaſticall Canon they doe this.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Titulo</hi> 45. The Latin Biſhops are acceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie to the death of Chriſtian people, the Pope eſpecially, who pronounceth the kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of Chriſtians, ſuch as reſiſt the Papacie, bleſſed and happy.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> The twelueth Article is the Euchariſt and Liturgie, which the Latins call Maſſe, which
I reduce to thoſe heads.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. They vſe vnleauened bread for leaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, belying <hi>Peter</hi> and his Succeſſours, as if they had this by tradition from them.</item>
                  <item>2. They take not bread of any quantitie, they breake not the bread, they diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute it not, as the Lord deliuered it in his myſticall Supper; only the Prieſt ſwalloweth vp a morſell of vnleauened bread, of the bigneſſe of a farthing.</item>
                  <item>3. Only he that ſacrificeth is partaker of the ſacrifice; as for the reſt, whether they be of the Clergie or of the Laity, they are made partakers of it by a kiſſe. Neither hath that ſaying any place with them,<note place="margin">Calumnie.</note> who eateth my fleſh and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:16551:33"/>
drinketh my blood hath life eternall: ſeeing they are not pertakers of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and blood of Chriſt: they commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate neuer but in the<note n="a" place="margin">Preparation to the Paſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer.</note> 
                     <hi>paraſcene,</hi> and the houre of death<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and then they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue no<note n="b" place="margin">Vnleauened bread,</note> 
                     <hi>Azymes</hi> conſecrated, but only a bitte of another bread, common, and not bleſſed: and they render a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of it ſo, becauſe they know not who is worteh of it; which excuſe doth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wray another fault worthy of blame, to wit, that they vſe no Confeſſors: for if they had vſe of thoſe, they would not be ignorant of this point.</item>
                  <item>4. Whoſoeuer are partakers of the ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, that is of the Euchariſt waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their mouthes,<note place="margin">Calumnie.</note> they put out the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter out of their mouthes vpon the earth and trample it vnder their feete. If ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore theſe miſteries bee Chriſts, why are they ſo diſhonoured? and if they be diſhonoured, how are they Chriſts?</item>
                  <item>5. They celebrate Maſſe in the morning, a time not appointed by the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke Church.</item>
                  <item>6. One and the ſame Prieſt celebrateth Maſſe twiſe or thriſe a day; either on the ſame Altar or on another; and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine many Prieſts ſucceſsiuely vpon the ſame Altar.</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:16551:33"/>7. They contemne the Liturgie made by Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>8. In the Lent they ſay Maſſe euery day.</item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> The thirteenth Article, is Confirmation, (as the words of the Index beare) reiected by the Grecia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: The words are theſe: When the Baptized is come to age, and is now ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to actuall ſinne, they annoynt him with Oyle for remiſſion of ſins; and ſo they ſeeme to baptize twice.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> The fourteenth Article is in Baptiſme: they Baptize with once dipping, pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing theſe words, In the Name of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Sonne, and Holy Ghoſt. They baptize onely with water, and they annoynt him that is to bee baptized, with Spittle, powred out vpon the palme of the left hand, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine taking it in the right hand, they anoynt the baptized with it; neither receiue they from the Catholike Church the appoynted oyntment.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="15"/> The fifteenth Article is concerning Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination: Biſhops at euery occaſion conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate not the Cleargie, and Biſhops but ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in the yeare, and ſuperſtitiouſly keepe ſet dayes in the weeke at the Equinoctialls, and Solſtices; that is, in the Spring, Summer, Harueſt, and Winter; in March and Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, Iune and December; and that in the firſt weeke of March, but in the reſt of the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:16551:34"/>
moneths on the fourth day they ordaine Prieſts and Deacons, with others of the Clergy; but vpon Saterday they ordaine Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, and others of the higher Orders.</p>
               <p>The Succeſſour of the dead Pope is cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen after this manner: The Synod chooſeth him, and bringeth him to the dead, the <note n="*" place="margin">The liuing is the whole, the dead the halfe, <hi>viz,</hi> a carkaſe. Calumnie.</note> whole to the halfe; and taking the dead Popes hand, they put it vpon the necke of the liuing Pope; and this they thinke to bee the Vnction and Conſecration of the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſour, who incontinent offereth ſacrifice for the ſafetie of the dead Pope; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after hee ſtoutly and couragiouſly taketh the pontificall Offices vpon him, as if hee were lawfully annoynted.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="16"/> The ſixteenth Article is Marriage, they make vnlawfull marriages; for two brethren marry two ſiſters, and when one in the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin Church giueth his Daughter in marriage to any man, he againe asketh the daughter of him<note n="*" place="margin">Conſoceri.</note> that is Father in Law to his Daughter for his Sonne, brother or kinsman.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They ſhut vp all Prieſts and Deacons from marriage by their Lawes, and they hold it an abomination to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the Sacrament from a married Prieſt.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If any married man be initiated in Prieſt-hood or Deaconſhip, he muſt quit his wife and leaue her; and this
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:16551:34"/>
by a very ſtrict Law, they command to be kept in all the prouinces ſubiect vnto them: but many were amongſt them, who vilipended this Law, and married a ſecond wife after the death of the firſt, and ſo ſome married the third, and yet they remained ſtill in their ſacred Office.</p>
               <p n="4">4. There are many Churchmen amongſt them, who commit whordome, and all kind of vncleaneſſe moſt ſecurely without puniſhment, taking their whores in the night time to their chambers, and letting them againe depart being vailed; neither doe they account this to be an act of vnclea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but only an idle dreame or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parition.</p>
               <p>Thus farre they accuſe the Latines doctrine and Sacraments; now follow the errours which they impute to them in their man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The firſt errour in manners and cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, not ſo eſſentiall to the ſubſtance of Religion as they hold the reſt, is this; Their Prieſts vſe a certaine purging and waſhing, which ſerues, as they ſay, for remiſsion of ſinnes, and yet it is meerely Iudaiſme.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Their principall Biſhops entring to their Maſſe in a Proceſsion, haue little naked children going before them, whom they
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:16551:35"/>
ſprinckle with water, affirming that this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth them inuincibly ſtrong in warrs.</p>
               <p n="3">3. They vſe the holy Euchariſt moſt neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently,<note place="margin">Here there is ſome Calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny.</note> for going to the fields or countrey, they carry it without light, and giue it to the people without light; and thoſe fellowes that follow the warres carry it in their burſe, or put it vp after ſuch a faſhion.</p>
               <p n="4">4. In the ſummer ſolſtice they gather the bones of impure beaſts; as Aſſes, Dogges, and ſuch like; they burne them and put the aſhes of them in water, affirming that they ſerue for the purging and expiation of thoſe perſons whom they ſprinckle with them.</p>
               <p>In the beginning of Lent, which is the fourth day called Wedneſday, with theſe aſhes mingled with water, they ſprinckle all the Prieſts that come, on the forehead and face, thinking thereby to giue aide and helpe to their faſt. It is reported that they mingle theſe aſhes with the bread that they eate. O how great and how ſtrange an abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination is this!</p>
               <p n="5">5. Vpon Eaſter day, being the Lords day, they kill a Lambe and roaſt it, they bring it vnto the Altar, and then to their Table. Which Ceremonies being finiſhed, they eate the fleſh of the Lambe and burne the bones, and keepe the aſhes all the yeare long, to ſprinckle thoſe whom they would haue to be bleſſed. They kill and are killed, they
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:16551:35"/>
commit murther, how then can their Prieſts with thoſe bloody hands, offer the myſticall body and blood of Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Vpon the Lords paſsion day, they build the Lords Tombe within the Church, with common and baſe cloathes ordained for quotidian vſe, and running to this Tombe they worſhip it no leſſe, than if it were that ſame Tombe wherein the Lords body was laid. Afterwards euery man pulleth to him his owne cloathes againe, and vſeth them for couering of his body, ſanctifying a prophane thing, and prophaning that which is holy, and ſo pull downe that Tombe like a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane Stage, which a little before was ſo worſhipped by them; ſporting with things which are not matters of ieaſting: like little children building cabinets of ſtraw, which a little after they beate downe.</p>
               <p n="7">7. They vſe the Altar in ſtead of their common Table, and the linnen belonging to the ſame; which from the ſacrifice they bring to their ſupper, and from their ſupper to the Sacrifice againe.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Any man that pleaſeth may approach to the Altar, yea when the action is in hand, and that without regard of Sexe, Age, or Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; and Layicks ſit with Prieſts and other holy Orders: yea, they plead Actions at the Altar. Sometimes the ſame Layicks carry Spurres vpon their heeles, and carrying rods
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:16551:36"/>
in their hands, they keepe a foule noiſe. Yea, before the Altar they are bold euen to doe thoſe things which they doe in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moneſt Court in all the Country. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times women ſit in the Chaire of a Biſhop, for thoſe that among the Latins are moſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent in piety, can no bettter diſcerne ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things from prophane. Yea, which is worſe, they ſuffer Dogges to enter into the Church; and when the Prieſt is a ſacrificing and celebrating the Hoaſt, which they hold to be life giuing bread; they ſuffer the Dogs ſitting at the Prieſts feete, to barke at all thoſe that come in, and to fawne vpon the Prieſts and others that ſtand by. They ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer Beares and Hogges alſo to enter into the Church.</p>
               <p n="9">9. When the Goſpel is a reading, and Maſſe a ſinging; yea, when the very ſacred gifts are taking out, all men who pleaſe ſit, and yet they are neuer blamed by their Leaders. When wee aske the cauſe of this irreuerent and vndecent geſture, they anſwere, that they ſit, that no tumult be raiſed, whereby God may bee offended; as if that vnſeemely and irreligious ſitting were not iniurious to God, but rather tending to his honour.</p>
               <p n="10">10. After Table, they take not the <hi>Panagia,</hi> or bleſſing in honor of the moſt holy Mother of God, but they mocke at vs for the ſame, as if wee Grecians onely tooke the bleſſing
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:16551:36"/>
when our bellies are full of meat and drinke: and ſo they eſteeme a thing holy of it ſelfe, prophane. Theſe forſooth, are the men that are bold to ſay, that they are moſt religiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly minded towards the moſt holy Mother of God.</p>
               <p n="11">11. They nick-name the Grecians which are moſt pious in their actions, calling them <hi>Bogomili:</hi> they ſay that the Armenians are more religious then the Greekes, whom they call Brethren, and whom they loue as bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren; yea, they hate vs more cruelly then Iewes and Saracens: for they honour and embrace Iewes, which amongſt them may carry the old Teſtament in their hands.</p>
               <p n="12">12. If any man amongſt them die by the ſword, hee is thought to bee bleſſed, and to goe ſtraight to Paradiſe, though he be killed fighting out of auarice, or for murther, or for any other wicked deed.</p>
               <p n="13">13. Whatſoeuer death any man dieth amongſt them, they euer blame<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, I thinke to bee <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>; for in the Weſterne parts they vſe to blame For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune much.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, for ſo after a barbarous manner they name Fortune or Deſtiny.</p>
               <p n="14">14. They ſhaue their beards, and all the haires of their body, holding this in a manner for expiation, which is meere Iudaiſme.</p>
               <p n="15">15. They eate dead things and ſtrangled, things taken from wild beaſts, blood, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane things, as Hogges, Beares, Conies, Hares, Snailes, Water-dogs, Mice, Crowes,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:16551:37"/>
Rauens, Dolphins, and ſuch like vncleane beaſts.</p>
               <p>And ſo much for that which the Grecians taxe in the Doctrines and Ceremonies of the Latines; now followeth that which they taxe, ſome things iuſtly, and ſome things vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtly, in their habit.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The Pope and his Vicars vſe a Miter, and a Turkiſh tuffe, with long robes, and other things vſed in the old Teſtament, more fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting for women.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Their Prieſtly veſture is not of wooll, to ſignifie Chriſt ſlaine like a Lambe for vs, but of ſilke party-coloured. When they are do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing holy Seruice, they carry their Gloues in both their hands; and vpon the right hand they write, <hi>Tanquam ex nube,</hi> and vpon the left, <hi>Agnus Dei.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Their Biſhops vſe rings alwayes, and they giue this reaſon: Becauſe that they are like Bridegromes, or rather Husbands, euer mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to their Churches; ſo groſſe are their thoughts of ſacred matters.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Their Eccleſiaſticke perſons and Monkes vſe no other daily veſture then Layickes vſe; neither ſhalt thou euer diſcerne Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men from prophane men, ſince they ſhaue the chin, and that women-like: <hi>Gloria enim eorum inconfuſione,</hi> for their glory is their ſhame: their ordinary clothing is of haire; the veſture for holy dayes is all ſilke, directly
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:16551:37"/>
repugnant to the Conſtitutions of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Church. Some Monkes alwayes vſe white robes, a token (as they ſay) of vertue and cleanlineſſe in them.</p>
               <div type="supplement">
                  <head>A Supplement.</head>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> They ſuffer Prieſts and men of other Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to lye eight dayes without buriall, and that for filthy lucre and gaine.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> They celebrate ſundry of the feſtiuities of Chriſt vntimely, and confuſedly, not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the tradition of the Fathers.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Whomſoeuer they looſe from excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, they ſtrip them naked to the loynes, and hauing whipt them ſoundly, they let them goe, as then being perfectly reconciled to the Church.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> They receiue not the workes of Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome, Baſil,</hi> and <hi>Gregory Nazianzen,</hi> the lights of the Church.<note place="margin">There are ſome calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies heere.</note> They contemne the Epiſtles of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> ſaying, that hee was not one of the twelue, and that hee did not ſee Chriſt, regarding nothing that viſion which hee ſaw going to Damaſcus, when it was ſaid, <hi>Vas electionis eris;</hi> neither regard they his ſtripes, trauailes, and conuerſion of Gentils. Herein, as in ſome other, the Greeks falſely charge the Latins.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cerularius,</hi> Archbiſhop Patriarch of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople in his Epiſtle to <hi>Peter,</hi> Patriarch
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:16551:38"/>
of Antioch, in briefe tearmes &amp; ſhort words gathereth all theſe long poynts, and conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth out of his narration, that ſince the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines are ſuch men and ſo giuen, it is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible that they ſhould haue any vnion with them, or hold them to bee true and Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox Chriſtians; or ſuffer and endure them to bee numbred with them. And that which he holdeth to be moſt grieuous and intolerable, is the Supremacie challenged by the Latine Church, to teach all, and to bee taught of none, and Dictator-like to giue Lawes to binde other Churches, whereas ſhee doth thoſe things which others miſlike in her. This (gentle Reader) thou ſhalt finde in <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronius</hi> his Annals, <hi>Tomo XI. anno Chriſti,</hi> 1054. <hi>num.</hi> 33. where <hi>Baronius</hi> ſtriueth to excuſe the true things laid to their charge, to refute the vntruths, and to cloke the errours of this Weſterne Church in things rebukeable. Yea, hee bringeth in <hi>Petrus Antiochenus</hi> writing an anſwere to <hi>Cerularius,</hi> and doing it with greater credit to the cauſe, (if he wrote ſuch an anſwere) and in more modeſt and Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an tearmes then any Sides-man could haue done: ſeeing that preiudice oftentimes lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the beſt man that is, either in anſwering to be Satyricke and invectiue, or elſe to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the abſurdeſt and moſt erronious things that can be; And therefore I will ſet downe his Epiſtle, becauſe it is profitable for theſe
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:16551:38"/>
times in which we liue, wherein euery man would draw another to his opinion and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe in all things; in things of themſelues meerly indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, in things touching Verity, Schiſme, or Hereſie: for Nature hath made man <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, a ciuil creature and ſociable, delighting in the company of thoſe that are of his owne Species, and deſiring all thoſe that are of his owne kind to ſympathize with his mind and affection. But Chriſtian Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſuffereth many things, tolerating that in the weake, which in the ſtronger it would whip with a ſcourge, before it ſhould come to bee Schiſmaticall, either in action or affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. The Lord ioyne the Chriſtian Church in vnitie of faith, and Communion in Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <head>The Letter of <hi>PETRVS AN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIOCHENVS to CERV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LARIVS.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>WHat is it to vs that their Prieſts ſhaue their beards? And what al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they carry a Ring as a Badge of their Marriage with the holy and bleſsed Church?<note n="*" place="margin">This place ſeemeth to bee forged; for it was Chriſt that was crowned diſgracefully with thornes, and not <hi>Peter;</hi> or elſe <hi>Peter</hi> is put for Chriſt: for fewe are ſo mad to aſcribe ſo much honor to <hi>Peter:</hi> but no Grecian of Antiochia I am ſure.</note> Wee alſo beare a Crowne on our heads, for the honour (without doubt) of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:16551:39"/>
                           <hi>Peter</hi> Prince of the Apostles, vpon whom the Church was built: for what thoſe wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men inuented to the reproach of that holy One, wee doe piouſly to his glory and honour; the <hi>Romanes</hi> ſhauing their beards, wee bearing our Crowne vpon our heads:<note n="*" place="margin">To wit, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiochians.</note> Wee alſo are adorned with gold; our Gloues, our Handkerchiefes, and our Stoles are imbroydered with gold. Whereas they eat vncleane things, and their Monkes eate fleſh and hogges greaſe, if thou wilt enquire diligently, thou ſhalt find that ſome of vs doe the like; for the <hi>Bethinians, Lydes,</hi> and <hi>Thracians</hi> eate the Pye, little Crowes, Turtles, and earth. Conies, the vſe of which our Fathers left to vs as indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent: for there is none of Gods creatures to bee reiected, but all are to bee receiued with thankeſgiuing, which wee learne of that great veſſell of linnen which came downe from heauen: for as <hi>Baſil</hi> ſaith, In hearbes and rootes, that which is hurtfull wee ſeparate from the reſt: ſo in fleſh wee make diſtinction betweene profitable and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:16551:39"/>
hurtfull, for Hemlocke is an hearbe as the Rauen is fleſh, &amp;c. Whereas they eate ſtrangled, and two Brethren marry two Siſters, I beleeue theſe things are done without the Popes permiſsion, &amp;c. In Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople, and with vs alſo thou ſhalt finde many ſuch things done, &amp;c. See therefore, my very venerable Lord, how wee neglecting many things which are done amiſſe amongst our ſelues, are too cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious to prie into other mens buſineſſe, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt wee ſhould bee reforming our owne Errours.</p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <p>I will not diſpute now, whether <hi>Petrus</hi> euer wrote ſuch a Letter; but ſurely this I muſt ſpeake, <hi>(Cum omnium piorum bona ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia)</hi> the Letter ſmelleth of Mildneſſe and Charitie: and would to God the Romane Church and <hi>Baronius</hi> would vſe the aduiſe of this Writer, in dealing with the reſt of the Churches of <hi>Europe,</hi> it would ſaue much Chriſtian blood from being ſhed in <hi>Europe</hi> now adayes.</p>
                  <p>And as we haue ſeene the ſtrictneſſe of the Greekiſh humours, againſt all the Weſterne Churches, and ſeeing the Reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:16551:40"/>
now adayes, are in many of theſe points culpable alſo by their iudgement; ſo now let vs heare what things the Latins doe obiect a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaiſt them on the other ſide, and that, as they are collected by Maſter <hi>Hugo Aetherianus,</hi> ſo neere as we can.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The Latins obiect to them their capri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious pride, who would draw all the world to Greekiſh Ceremonies. <hi>Caleca lib.</hi> 4. rebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth this in them.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. They eate leauened bread in the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Vpon Eaſter day, when the people is to communicate, their preparation is cold, they conſecrate too much, and which is not tollerable, they burne the reliques.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. They dippe the Bread in Wine, and giue it to the Communicants in a ſpone.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Their Deacons being promoued, take wiues for feare they loſe their dignitie, which is againſt the tenth Canon of the <hi>Nycen</hi> Synod.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Their Prieſts are men of blood for the moſt part, which we our ſelues did ſee fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the Emperour through <hi>Capadocia</hi> &amp; the <hi>Perſian</hi> Regions.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Their Princes make the Prieſts ſtand by them at their banquets, taking their due ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour from them.</p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:16551:40"/>8. For little or very light cauſes they whippe their Clergie with ropes, as if they were Pagans.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. Their Biſhops are right in <hi>Simon Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus</hi> eſtate, for they giue no Churches with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out money, no Orders without their hands bee full, no Chriſtian buriall without money.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. Their Patriarchs, Archbiſhops and Prieſts (as it was in the Primitiue Church with hereticks) are all promoued by Layicks. Alſo the third Canon of the Synod, which the Grecians call the ſeuenth great Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell maketh all ſuch promotion of none ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. They deny the proceſsion of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpirit from the Sonne. They faſt but one Saturday in the whole yeare.<note n="*" place="margin">Saturday be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Eaſter called <hi>Sanctu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Sabbatum.</hi>
                     </note> Mans nature from the beginning is ſet on euill, but the Grecians gut contendeth with its ruine; they keepe no dyet in eating. They ſcarſely faſt ſeuen dayes in the whole Lent; yea in the whole yeare: for in all their faſting they eate their Supper, except on fiue dayes in Lent, and that in the begining of their weeke, and on the holy Sabbath, and on the Eue of the Epiphanie. They cut away the great weeke from the Lent, ſo their faſt is but ſixe weekes; from the which ſixe weekes, if thou takeſt the ſixe Sundayes with the ſixe Saturdayes, ſcarce is their faſt but thirty daies; for on
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:16551:41"/>
Sundayes and Saturdayes they faſt not.</p>
                  <p n="12">12. Their Monkes liuing without the Monaſtaries, like beaſts are found in the ſtreets eating fruite or any meate, drawing it out of their boſom as out of a cheſt or coffin. They goe to Tauernes, they haue not all common in one burſſe, but euery one hath his owne, none of their Monkes ſhaue, which is directly againſt the Apoſtle, who ſaith,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.14.</note> 
                     <hi>Si comam nutriat &amp;c.</hi> If a man vſe long hayre it is a reproach vnto him: they diuide their haire on their foreheads like women.</p>
                  <p n="13">13. Women leauing their naturall orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, adorne themſelues with the haires of the dead, which is directly againſt the words of <hi>Peter</hi> in his firſt Epiſtle 3. <hi>Chap.</hi> 3. <hi>verſe. Let no women vſe imbrodered haire or borrowed, &amp;c.</hi> Women paint themſelues with purpure and white fard or painting; and when the Husband diſpleaſeth the Wife, or the Wife the Husband, they goe before the Pretor of the City; and ſo laying downe their Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and cutting their girdles, they chooſe where they liſt other Mates againſt Chriſts owne Canon: <hi>quod Deus coniunxit, &amp;c.</hi> That which God hath ioyned let no man ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate.</p>
                  <p n="14">14. In their houſes they haue little Cab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bines, in which they place the Images of Saints; they giue them all worſhip with Lamps, Waxe, Incenſe, and they ſuffer the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:16551:41"/>
Synod at Churches no become a wildernes; they celebrate Maſſe in their bed-Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers for the moſt part.</p>
                  <p n="15">15. The Prieſt ſayes Maſſe at three of the Clocke, hauing almoſt no Auditours except his wife or his Child; and ſo when hee ſayes <hi>pax vobis,</hi> hee ſayes it commonly to the bare walls.</p>
                  <p n="16">16. The Prieſts wiues come to the Altar, and doe the office of a Deacon; they take the bread from the Altar, or any other thing, euen to their ordinary vſe.</p>
                  <p n="17">17. On all Sundayes and Sabbaths of Lent they ſay Maſſe, and make the Lords body; but on the reſt of the daies they regard it not, except vpon an vrgent occaſion; vſing only <hi>prae ſanctificatis:</hi> in the Lent they alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether omit <hi>Deus Dominus &amp; illuxit nobis,</hi> which they ſing in the reſt of the yeare.</p>
                  <p n="18">18. The Prieſts haue long beards after the manner of the Iewes, which when they drink the Lords blood are drenched with it. They eate ſtrangled blood, they feed Hogs with mans blood.</p>
                  <p n="19">19. When they aſſemble themſelues to bury the dead, euery friend and kinſman gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the dead a kiſſe after a Pagan rite; for the Pagans were wont to ſpeake theſe words to the dead, <hi>Vade cum natura te vocauerit; ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quemur te.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="20">
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:16551:42"/>20. They ſay, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, Chriſt, cannot doe ſo much as <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, Lord; therefore they ſay often <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> but neuer <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> in their ſeruice.</p>
                  <p n="21">21. The Monkes as (it ſeemeth) only haue power to bind and looſe, which Chriſt gaue to <hi>Peter</hi> and his Succeſſours; wherefore Prieſts for Lucre take vpon them moſt filthy Monaſtique habite and remit ſinnes, only that they may gaine money.</p>
                  <p n="22">22. They auer that the Latines haue no Sacrament, becauſe they conſecrate vnlea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uened bread; for which damnable opinion they muſt be Hereticks ſaith <hi>Aetherianus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="23">23. If a Latin Prieſt offer vpon their Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar (which ſcarſe is permitted) they waſh the Alter with water before they offer any thing vpon it againe. And if a Latine woman bee married to a Greeke Husband, ſhee is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to abiure the Latin Communion, her Baptiſme, and the Lords Body which ſhee did eate in the Latine Church, her confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and her faſt vpon Saterdayes. Likewiſe if a Latin man marry a woman in the Citie of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> he muſt renounce and abiure the Latin Church: the Greekiſh Prieſts pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe much, but they performe nothing: they rebaptize thoſe that come from the Latin Church to them.</p>
                  <p>The reſt of the things which are obiected to them, are euen the ſame which they ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to the Latins. So wee ſee the fruite of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:16551:42"/>
their Schiſme to be the malicious imputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of many infamous lies and damnable ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies, worthy to be buried in the gulfe of obliuion: for though ſome of theſe imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions be true, yet moſt of them are Calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies on both ſides, or at leaſt, things not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of rebuke.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="list_of_authors">
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:16551:43"/>
            <head>The names of the Authours which haue written for Grecians againſt the Latines.</head>
            <list>
               <item>1 <hi>Photius Patriarcha Conſtan.</hi> obiected the proceſſion of the Holy Ghoſt from the Son, as an Hereſie to the Latine Church, <hi>anno</hi> 876. <hi>Baron. annal.</hi> He wrote a Booke <hi>De proceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſione S. Sancti;</hi> it is in the Bauarian <hi>Biblioth. num.</hi> 115.</item>
               <item>2 <hi>Nicolaus Epiſcopus Methonae,</hi> wrote a Booke <hi>de proceſsione S. Sancti Bib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lioth. Bavar. num.</hi> 116. Hee wrote alſo another of all the Controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies of Faſting, of Lent, and of the Marriage of Prieſts, <hi>numero</hi> 101.</item>
               <item>3 <hi>Nicetas Pectoratus,</hi> refuted by <hi>Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertus.</hi> His poſitions are in <hi>Bibliot. Bav. numero</hi> 120.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:16551:43"/>4 <hi>Metropolita Nicaenus, hoc eſt Euſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>5 <hi>Michael Cerularius,</hi> of whom wee ſpake.</item>
               <item>6 <hi>Theophylactus Bulgariae Epiſcopus.</hi> His Booke is in <hi>Bibl. Bav. numero</hi> 116. <hi>vixit anno</hi> 1073.</item>
               <item>7 <hi>Maximus Planudes Bav. num.</hi> 115. Hee liued vnder <hi>Andronicus Palaeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logus</hi> the elder.</item>
               <item>8 <hi>Nicolaus Cabaſilas, qui ſcripſit contra Aquinatem.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>9 <hi>Germadius Bulgariae Epiſcopus, Bav. numero</hi> 118.</item>
               <item>10 <hi>Iob Monabus</hi> wrote an Apologie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Popes Supremacy, <hi>exſtat in Bav.</hi> He liued vnder <hi>Michael</hi> and <hi>Theodora,</hi> Emperours.</item>
               <item>11 <hi>Nilus Archiepiſcopus Theſſalon.</hi> wrot 49 Bookes againſt the Latines; chiefly hee wrote againſt the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsion of the holy Ghoſt, and the Popes Supremacie. His booke is in <hi>Bibl. Bav. num.</hi> 124.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:16551:44"/>12 <hi>Marcus Metropolita Epheſi,</hi> was in the Florentine Councell a deadly enemy to the Latin Church; retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the Orient, hee broke all concord, and wrote many bookes againſt the Latins, <hi>Bav. num.</hi> 102. <hi>&amp;</hi> 115.</item>
               <item>13 <hi>Metropolitani Achrideni prima &amp; ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunda congreſsio, num.</hi> 116.</item>
               <item>14 <hi>Palamas contra Beccum.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>15 <hi>Michael Patriarcha. Poſſevinus in fine apparatus.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>16 <hi>Germanus Patriarcha Conſtantinop. Poſſev. appar.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>17 <hi>Metrophanes Epiſcopus Smyrnenſis. Heidelb.</hi> 216.</item>
               <item>18 <hi>Hieremias Patriarcha Conſt.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>19 <hi>Maximus Margunius Epiſcopus Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therorum.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="list_of_authors">
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:16551:44"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The names of Authors which haue</hi> written againſt the Grecians for the Latins, whereof ſome were Grecians.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1</hi> Emanuel Caleca, Bib. Bav.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2</hi> Demetrius Cydonius contra Cabaſilam. Poſſ. appar.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3</hi> Beccus pat. Conſt. Bav. num. <hi>115.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4</hi> Beſſarion Cardinalis plurima ſcripſit.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5</hi> Gennadius Pat. Conſt. <hi>for defence of the Councell of Florence.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6</hi> Gregorius Pat. Conſt. Bib. Bav. num. <hi>115.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7</hi> Georgius Trapezuntius ad Monachos, ibidem.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>8</hi> Iulianus Cardinalis Poſſev.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>9</hi> F. Iohannes ord. praedicat. &amp; F. Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſcus.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>10</hi> Nichephorus Blemmida Grecian. Cal. lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>10.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>11</hi> Andreas Scocares. Poſſev. <hi>citeth him.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>12</hi> Andreas Epiſcopus Megerenſis, Poſſev. Catal. Sirleti.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:16551:45"/>
                  <hi>13</hi> Fautinus Vallarenſis Cretenſis Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiep. <hi>wrote againſt the hinderers of the Vnion with the Latines,</hi> Catal. Sirleti.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>14</hi> Leo X. Papa.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>15</hi> Humbertus Cardinalis Tomo XI. Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron. <hi>againſt</hi> Archidrenus Bulgariae Epiſc. &amp; Nicetas Pectoratus.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>16</hi> Thomas contra Graecorum errores.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>17</hi> Barlaam de Seminaria <hi>wrote Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles againſt the Grecians,</hi> Tom. <hi>5.</hi> antiq, Lect. D. Henrici Caniſij.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>18</hi> S. Anſelmus <hi>wrote</hi> De proceſsione S. Sancti cont. Grecos.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>19</hi> Hugo Aetherianus <hi>wrote 3. Bookes</hi> de proc. S. Sancti cont. Grecos, Tom. <hi>9.</hi> Biliot. SS.PP.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>20</hi> Antonius Meſſana cont. errores Graec.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>21</hi> Latinus quidem demorans in ſuburbiis Pariſiorum ad Palaeologum Imperato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem peregrinum in Gallia, Catal. Vati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can. Poſſevini.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>22</hi> Disputatio qua duo Theologi diſſerunt de proceſsione S. Sancti, viz. Manuel
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:16551:45"/>
Chryſolora cum Georgio Palama Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trop. Theſſalonic. Poſſevinus <hi>holdeth this to be a Dialogue onely.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>23 Laſtly, all the Councells which confirme the Proceſsion of the holy Spirit, eſpecially</hi> Florence, <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed both in Greeke and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, in which the Proceſsion of the holy Spirit is moſt euidently ſhewen.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <lg>
               <l>HEere faults eſcap'd I haue amended,</l>
               <l>Therefore Reader be not offended;</l>
               <l>But if thou wilt: then whoſe to blame</l>
               <l>Thy foſtred faults if others name?</l>
            </lg>
            <p>In the Preface. For rigorous, read vigorous. In C. read <hi>magis diligentiam.</hi> for Crow, r. Crane. for <hi>Iekan,</hi> r. <hi>Iehan.</hi> for crit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke, r. crypticke, for vntie, r. vntied. Page 3. in <hi>marg.</hi> for <hi>Loe,</hi> r. <hi>Leo.</hi> for <hi>lib.</hi> r. <hi>ſub.</hi> p. 8. line 11. for the, r. thy. p. 13. l. 14. for our, r. one. p. 14. l. 12. for <hi>Barnious,</hi> r. <hi>Baronius,</hi> pa 15. l. 3. for chiefe, r. cheefe. l. 26. for fiſh, r. fiſt. pag. 17. l. 3. r. to the Sea. lin 24. for <hi>concimantes,</hi> r. <hi>concinnantes</hi> pag. 18. li. 4. for <hi>iudice,</hi> r. <hi>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dice.</hi> p. 20. l. 10. for worteh, r. wotthy. p. 36. l. 5. for coffin, r. coffer. pa. 37. l. 1. for Synod at, r. Synodall. for no, r. to.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
